So we've gone over all the different code groups, all the different areas like the stage, our sprites
and a bunch more.
At this stage you have a really good understanding of all the areas, but there are a few things we
have not covered yet.
And in order to give you a full understanding of how this whole scratch environment works in this lesson,
we will do just that.
And I think the best way to do this is by going from the left side of the screen to the right side of
the screen to make sure we cover everything.
So firstly, starting at the top left of our screen, we have code.
And you know what this is all about.
It's our code.
But moving just a bit to the right you will see we have costumes.
Now we haven't talked about this yet, but every sprite that we have in our program can have as many
costumes as you like.
And all these costumes are specific to that sprite.
So remember how we made our cat walk across the screen by adding the code next costume?
Well, that used these two costumes to create the walking effect.
And the cool part here is that scratch gives you so much control to create new costumes and edit the
ones that you have.
Like for example, I could go to the second costume for the sprite.
I click on the tail here and just rotate it down a bit.
Then let's activate the walking script again.
Now you'll see how the cat's tail moves when it walks as well, but it doesn't stop there.
We could also import new costumes either from Scratch's library, upload our own, or even draw our
own custom costume, which is where your artistic skills will come into play.
Anyways, you'll understand how these costumes work when we build our own in our games and animations
in future lessons.
Moving one tab over here you can see we have sounds and this is quite similar to costumes, except here
you can see this cat sprite comes pre-installed with this meow sound, which we used earlier.
And again, you can upload your own sounds or choose from some of the sounds that are available on scratch.
You can add a lot more depth to our character and objects in our program using sound.
Now, one more thing to know about costumes and sound is that both of them are controlled by these two
groups of code, so the looks code group can control our costumes and the sound group can control our
sounds for our sprite.
Let's keep moving to the side.
Here we have our script editor where all our code goes, and you know all about that.
Then we have our green flag and our stop button.
Moving across, we have these buttons here which allow you to change the layout of our interface.
But I think this layout is pretty good at the moment in the best.
So we'll leave that.
And at the edge there is a full screen button so we can see our program in all its glory.
And moving down.
We have our code viewer, which you also know about.
It's where the action happens and then down again.
We have this area which we have not yet discussed.
Firstly, we can change the name of our sprite.
So instead of being sprite one we can call it cat.
And moving across you can see we have these x and y inputs.
And this is an important concept.
So pay close attention.
X and y coordinates are like the positions for everything that happens on the scratch stage.
This helps us know where things are and how to move them around.
Like, imagine a giant grid covering the entire scratch stage with horizontal lines and vertical lines
crossing each other.
The grid is made up of x and y coordinates.
The x coordinate represents the horizontal position, or the left and right position of the sprite on
the stage, and the y coordinate represents the vertical position or the up and down of the sprite on
the stage.
Now let's think of it like a like a treasure map.
The x and y coordinates are like the instructions on how many steps to take in each direction to find
the treasure.
If we're told to take ten steps, right, and five steps up, we'd move ten steps along the x axis and
five steps along the y axis and scratch.
The stage has its own coordinate system with zero x and zero y being the center point.
The x coordinates range from -240 to 240, while the y coordinates range from -180 to 180.
When you want to move a sprite to a specific spot on the stage, you simply set its x and y coordinates.
For example, let's say we want to move our cat sprite to the top right corner of the stage.
We would then set the x coordinate to 240 and the y coordinate to 180.
You can also use the motion blocks in scratch like go to x 240 and y 180, or change y by minus five
to move your sprites around the stage using x and y coordinates.
Understanding X and Y coordinates is important for creating smooth animations and exciting games, as
it helps us position our sprites exactly where we want them on the stage, and that is why they are
so important.
Okay, moving down again, you can see we have the ability to show and hide our sprite, and this is
something we could also do with code under the look section.
And moving across we can change the size and direction of the sprite is pointing, which we can also
do under the looks code group.
Okay, moving down again, I think there's just one more thing we need to know and that's adding new
sprites in scratch.
You can have as many sprites as you want, and just like with costumes, you can use the sprites that
come with scratch.
You can upload your own or even create your own shapes and drawings.
Anyway, let's imagine we wanted to create a game where a dog chases a cat and you have to control the
cat to run away.
Here we could add a new sprite and we can search for dog.
And let's choose this one here.
And there you have it.
A brand new sprite.
And as you can see, it doesn't have any code in it because each sprite has its own code to control
it.
And also, like a cat sprite, this one comes with different costumes and sounds pre-installed and ready
for us to use.
There's just one more thing, which is the backdrops, which are pretty similar to sprites.
It's basically just the background behind the sprite.
So let's say our game is in the snow.
By clicking here, you can see we can change it to Arctic or desert or sea.
We can upload our own backdrop if we want, or we can even draw one.
Anyway, that's about it.
You are now a pro at the scratch environment, but now let's make you a pro programmer.